Yeah,
[Music]
okay. It's recording.
Um, so for for Joseph, for Daniel, for
the rest of the institute who's uh
following along remotely uh or via
YouTube, um welcome to the Active
Inference Institute. Uh we do a uh
weekly textbook group readings uh twice
on Thursdays, once in the morning, once
in the evening uh if you're if you're
roughly in the Western Hemisphere. And
um yeah, so so today we're going over
chapter 7 in cohort 7. Um and we'll be
talking about essentially the exemplar
discrete state space models and active
inference. That would be hidden markoff
models and uh partially observable
markoff decision-m processes. We have a
nice T-ise example which is pretty
classic in in the field as well as in
kind of behavioral and and and and
neuroscience and neur neuroiming studies
in general. And uh again we're in the
second half or part two of the book
which is highly dedicated to to
constructing uh essentially active
inference models as opposed to part one
which is much more focused on theory and
and definitions. Um, and so it's for
anyone who's interested in computational
modeling, whether it be doing it
themselves or getting a clearer grasp of
kind of what are these computational
models or cognitive models that we're
putting together in order to say
collaborate with a uh team of of people
who do do cognitive modeling, then it
it's very worthwhile to spend time with
the second half of the book. And then
furthermore, there are just there are
many discrete state spaces in in a in a
very general sense, in a in a physical
sense, in a kind of decision- making and
in in and human belief sense. It's
referring to scenarios where essentially
if we think about it in data, it's sort
of like categories. It's thinking about
binaries. uh it's not so much thinking
about uh fully continuous number series
such as a range over one through a
million where we could have so many
different
uh different values including with the
decimal points uh potentially an
infinite number of values instead we're
looking at
say RGB color scales on old television
so red blue green um we could have a
distribution between the three of them
in the sense of how much red how much
blue and how much screen. Uh but
nonetheless, it's it's a kind of um
discrete uh categorization process. So,
um yeah, normally I give a rather long
uh kind of chapter summary, but I'm
happy to just kind of open up the floor
if uh Joseph, you have any particular
questions or things you'd like to
discuss here.
Um I I would like to hear your summary.
Um I also do have some questions. Um I
haven't fully been able to understand
um for example figure 72. So it if we
could like I I I guess I just don't
understand what's plotted and and where
the lines are coming from. But
um yeah, I I'm I'm very interested in in
trying to build these models and
understand how to build them and um and
so this seems like a really critical
chapter for for me.
Yeah. Yeah. No, that's great. Um yeah,
figure 72, which I I personally have not
spent a lot of time with
recently, so coming back to it is rather
interesting. Yeah. Yeah. So the the this
is where the chapter it essentially
opens with hidden Markov models uh
before we jump up to uh partially
observable Markov decision-m processes.
So it's like we have um I believe my is
my screen still being shared
appropriately or can you not see
anything? Uh no I don't see your screen.
Okay, got it. Thanks for that. Just
realized I doing a little bit of
uh display gymnastics. Um that should
have done it. So this is and a quick
reference. This is the KOD for the
textbook group. And so we have this
available to all members and we have u
not just a overview of the textbook
group and you know dedicated uh meetings
and and time availability and and all
those sorts of things for the separate
cohorts. We also have a pretty good
breakdown of the active inference
textbook especially since it became open
source.
So, um, so yeah, figure 71, I know it's
not the one you referenced, but just to
make sure we're like familiar with it
enough, this is essentially a hidden
marov model. And so understanding kind
of the core dynamics here, uh, we al
ultimately only have three different
components in this model. So we have D,
our prior over initial states. It's kind
of like what are our beliefs about
states whenever we come into a situation
as it were. Um and then from there uh
that gets linked to uh observations that
we receive right and the relationship
between what we believe and sort of what
we see is linked through this this
likelihood matrix A. So it's represented
as kind of this broad categorical
probability distribution that is
conditional uh observations given our
beliefs S or in states S and then
there's also a temporal dynamic over
time right so we have the B matrix which
is kind of our beliefs about how
transitions change from one to another
so that's why we have this sort of state
at t minus one to state at t to state t
+ one. So it's this this temporal
dynamic playing out over discrete time
steps. Um and so from there you can move
to
7.2. A little bit of context. So this is
this is an example that relates to the
idea I believe it's of of someone who's
playing uh an instrument and they're
trying to actually play a song in accord
with the the script, the sheet music
that they're reading. And so we can
quickly imagine a scenario where there's
someone who is still learning how to
play. This is practice for them. Even if
it's someone who's very skilled, they're
maybe learning a new piece for like, I
don't know, an an orchestra performance
they'll be doing soon. Um, and so
there's all kinds of room for error,
right? And to to accidentally hit the
wrong notes at the wrong time. Maybe
you're still on beat, but uh but you
know, you you hit an A rather than an A
flat. And so that's sort of what this
this example is about is being able to
use the dynamics of a hidden markoff
model, including what notes play over
time and then also what does the
musician believe the note should be
versus what we we actually hear. Um,
right. And so so by being able to like
hear and it's obviously a very kind of
abstracted example. There's a lot more
to it there. We're not saying anything
about what the sheet music looks like,
but here we're just simplifying it to
saying the musician has a belief about
what the note should be versus what they
actually observe that they're they're
playing. And
so with this figure 7.2, I think the the
quickest way of kind of getting at what
the authors of the textbook are trying
to demonstrate for us as sort of an
illustrative example is this upper
right. This is like beliefs about hidden
states. So the agent believes that the
first note uh in terms of over time
should in fact be the first note as in
it's in row one. So that this this row
is like its own set of notes. Row two is
the uh yet another note. So it could be
read as like the top row is A. The
second row is A sharp. The next row is
B. The next row is C. Not to confuse
anyone who's not familiar with scales,
but we there is no B sharp essentially
unless you're concerned with naturals
and all that. So, um, so each row is its
own note. And then I here it's kind of
like the the musician believes based on
the sheet music that they should start
with the first note A and then move to A
sharp, move to B, move to C, and then go
back to A for the fifth note. So,
they're just kind of descending a
chromatic scale before they get back to
A again. That's what they believe should
happen. Meanwhile, with our O's or
observations, what really happens is
that we get an A, we get an A sharp, and
then rather than getting the expected B,
which is here, we the the actual
observation is that they realize, oh no,
they hit the same note twice in a row,
which is not correct. But by the fourth
time step, they get back to what the
note should be. And then here uh at time
step five they also hit the correct
note. So kind of what's what's happening
here is that there is at at S3 we would
say that this is prediction error,
right? And so with whenever the agent
infers their posteriors over hidden
states here they're so conditioned to
believe that it should be the right note
that that they kind of shaded this in as
if it's correct. But there's this
grayness here. It's very it's so light
but but essentially the idea is you know
this is the note that should have
happened their prior their observation
however gives them evidence that it's
actually this gray space this is maybe
actually the note that they heard um or
that they believe really happened. So
there there are aspects of this that can
seem kind of counterintuitive, but
really just being able to grasp that the
upper right are their beliefs about
states. The lower uh the lower right is
the observations they actually receive.
And then a good reminder is you know in
a discrete state space setting it's like
oh we're not looking at
you know the interim between A and A you
know some kind of microonal situation.
we're just looking at uh we're assuming
there's a and then there's a sharp and
then there's B and then there's C and
ultimately they're that's the western
scale of 12 notes um in the way that I'm
describing the example. So now these
these graphs on the left are a little
more complex um and it will be good to
spend a little bit of time with them.
I'll first just like read what it says
in the textbook. So, so we'll go with
lower left. We're looking at negative
free energy gradients or prediction
errors. The rate of change of the
beliefs in the upper left
plot is determined by the value of these
errors at each time step. And so what
we're seeing these are negative free
energy gradients. In terms of active
inference, we're wanting to minimize
prediction error. We're wanting to
minimize variational free energy. So if
these are actually negative gradients,
then that means that at each time step,
we should actually want these to be
rather large um if they're negative. And
so the the smaller they are, you know,
it's kind of like saying that it's sort
of the the worerer scenario. And then
that seems to kind of constrain the
agent's ability to to be confident or or
or kind of understand the the situation.
So um see and then
upper left beliefs posterior
probabilities about each note in the
sequence at each time step. Yeah. So the
these are the posterior probabilities.
It's kind of like their ability to
understand a particular note here of
what it should have been h has gone
down. Right? So there's a kind of
constraint there that's been applied.
And then once they start to hear the
correct notes again, their confidence
kind of it kind of increases. I will be
honest, these kinds of these two graphs
on the left, they're much more rarely
used today in active inference like
these specific types. It might be
because of this sort of kind of kind of
uh counterintuitive nature because more
often than not, we actually are looking
at you the inverse of the situation. So
we're looking at positive free energy.
And so actually this would look quite
bad. it would look like step three is
actually, you know, a rather good thing
in terms of minimizing uncertainty and
it's the other way around. But I I think
that the authors who who compose this
are really trying to get at a particular
kind of point by representing it this
way. Um I I think I'm still maybe a
little lost about
so um you said that just focusing on
this top left um the the y ais you said
is probability. So okay so I I get that
and what are all the different lines? Um
are are
these
different
trials or
um
one of the things
yeah one of the things I'm really
wanting to understand better is
um uh how the agent actually is learning
and and maybe that comes later on. This
is after this example. But
um where do do we adjust the weights of
this of the the in these matrices um
according to the result we get from our
minimization step? Oh yeah. No, that
that's an excellent question. Very
relevant. So so in this example, they
don't actually apply learning at all. So
this is essentially like a static model.
Yeah. Um, and I think they're just using
it to try and kind of get at the more
inference level dynamics as opposed to
learning. And so I I know that this is,
you know, this is pretty familiar
terminology for folks who do other forms
of kind of computational modeling, data
science, deep learning. Uh, I I heard
you say that, you know, referring to it
as adjusting the weights. All of that is
very relevant here. But so, so for this
particular model, yeah, there is no
learning. What would what could happen
is
that refer to this again. Um this what
typically what an agent learns are these
kind of probability
distributions over time. And so D you
know your your prior beliefs in the
basian sense those could be updated. So
you could the agent could effectively
learn its D matrix. um A could be
learned, B could be learned actually any
of its parameters, including C and E,
which C is just a prior over
observations. E is a prior over over
policies or actions. Um so, so that way
you know that's what's missing from this
and it's also missing from this because
we have no policy inference, right? So
the HMM is kind of like can be viewed as
a
truncated version of the POMDP which is
exactly equivalent until we get to here
this connection to to PI or representing
policies or action. And so so an HMM is
kind of like perception and no action.
uh partially observable markup
decision-making process is perception
and here we have the connection to
actions that it can take. So we get
these these kind of relationships where
suddenly state transitions the B
matrix recall earlier 7.2
two the B is simply what is the next
state going to be given the current
state. Whereas here we now
have yeah we now have what is the next
state going to be given the current
state as well as an action I take. So
that is sort of the kind of the the
agency so to speak that this this agent
has um in its ability to kind of infer
which actions to take and furthermore um
e the prior over policies I mean that so
that can be learned that gets
incorporated. C preferences prior over
observations there those are more often
left static. So those are more often
left static in the sense that they
become a kind of attracting point for
particular observations.
uh in that case that kind of supplies
the agent with a sort of goal. Um it
kind of like it's seeking out particular
observations that it it it prefers or
expects. Um in the sort of theoretical
literature, the idea is that it relates
to the notion of homeostasis. So, I
prefer to observe my blood oxygen level
being at a certain point or I prefer to
not observe my stomach growling because
usually it's a sign that I'm hungry and
I need to do something about that which
in a that context it would that that C
would then inform what I should do via
the B matrix of oh my stomach growling
must mean I'm hungry and I know that if
I eat food I will s I will no longer be
hungry at the next time step, so to
speak. Um, so, so again, any of these
can be learned, and I know that there's
a nice figure that kind of hits at the
point of this, but I don't want to get
us too lost in the weeds.
Um, hybrid
models, the essentially what happens is
that we end up with this kind of
hyperparameterization of all of those
model components. Okay, I'll stop I'll
stop scrolling around because there
might be that we missed that one. Still
relatively new. Um, so you would have
like a prior on D which itself is in the
discrete state space setting. So it
would be it would just be like a kind of
so it' be a deerishlay distribution. So
so it' be like a categorical
distribution but the values can in fact
exceed one. they don't have to sum to
one. You could almost think of it as a
kind of like dearishly count system
where it's like oh I I you know I have
my Dmatrix but then I've also
experienced like more of this state in
many more time steps. So it it implies
that there you that an agent actually
has a history of states and a history of
observations that it's kind of
accumulated and then that acts as a kind
of hyperparameter on these matrices
which then proceeds to modulate their
values and then learning them itself
will involve free energy minimization. I
it's just applying another free energy
minimization rule. Um and so and so like
minimizing free energy is sort of the
global uh functional or optimization
problem here for just about everything
like state like inferring states occurs
by minimizing variational free energy
inferring
policies heavily relies on uh minimizing
expected free energy which uh earlier on
in the textbook I think it's somewhere
in the realm of chapters 2 through or uh
there's kind of a broad
breakdown about those terms. So we
should be able to find those. We have
the equations as well. Yeah.
Great. So something we'll notice very
quickly between F and G. F is going to
be for again state inference which ends
up being treated as a separate process
related. But if if you were to code this
like if you were to write this in code,
you would actually write like separate
logics and even executions of state
inference versus policy inference. State
inference will involve min minimizing f
which without getting too lost in the
various ways we can break this down. We
could look at it as complexity minus
accuracy which is the sort of classic
you know machine learning imperative of
how do you create a model that can both
be generalizable and not excessively
complex and overfit um but we need it to
be accurate. So we don't want it to
heavily underfit either. Um so the the
complexity term there is just what is
the kale divergence between your
posteriors what you think now versus
your priors what you thought before and
then you want to also keep accuracy
high. So we want to be able to find the
expected value of the log of essentially
observations given x. So, so all this is
to say each one of these terms depending
on what the sign is in front of them um
we'll we'll want to either maximize or
minimize. So we'll want to maximize
accuracy right because it has a negative
sign in front of it. Vice versa for
complexity we actually want to minimize
that because at the end of the day we
come back to f we're just trying to
minimize that.
Um similarly for G. But the interesting
thing with G is that whenever we look at
just the top
line information gain and pragmatic
value we notice
that there are negative signs in front
of both of them and we're trying to
minimize G. So we actually here want to
maximize information gain. Meaning the
the the expected value of the kale
divergence between sort of what you your
posteriors what you what you think now
conditioned on what you've seen and what
you've done and the the the divergence
between that and just what you think now
versus or conditioned on what you have
done. So this is kind of like saying oh
now that I have actually observed the
outcomes of what I have done and what I
believe now versus simply just relying
on you know sort of what I've done. It
it it kind of prioritizes this idea of,
oh, I need to collect more observations,
and I actually want those observations
to be quite different from what I you
I'm used to seeing before, what I'm so
used to that I can practically sort of
marginalize them out. Right? So that
that's sort of the exploratory behavior
we see in active inference. And
furthermore, just the fact that we have
this functional that actually allows for
both exploratory behavior and pragmatic
value, which is simply your observations
conditioned on C. So like I mentioned
earlier, C it's often used for defining
like goals that the agent has. It's kind
of like the what you expect is what you
want, which is what will help you
maintain homeostasis or it's what will
help you achieve that goal that you have
in the far future or however you want to
look at it um or goal in the immediate
future. And so you want your
observations to essentially like you you
you want what you see to actually be
accurate versus like your priors over
observations, right? So that that's
that's kind of I don't know if you're
familiar with reinforcement learning,
but anything like epsilon greedy
behavior or having to like define manual
rules such as like oh you should always
exploit with a probability of 0.9 and
you know 10% of the time just do
something random and see see what
happens. instead instead this is what
defines exploratory behavior is directly
implicated in computing minimizing
expected free energy. So the that's the
claim in the textbook that these sort of
naturally balance out which
is not a sentence that really should be
said that way in the sense of you could
still have a scenario where a policy is
evaluated such that it might not have
any information gain at all. It's just
the fact
that both are computed and so there
there is no manual definition here.
We're just relying upon minimizing G and
these particular equations. I might have
gone much more deeply into that. And I I
hope I didn't miss No, I I really
appreciated that. I liked your
explanation about um the the the meaning
of those different distributions that
you're me measuring the kale divergence.
Um that that was very helpful actually
uh especially when you were talking
about the
uh information gain and the fact that
you know one is conditioned on why hat
or why tilda and one is not. Um I I had
I just sort of not connected those dots
before. So
um yeah.
Yeah. No problem at all. Can you say
again, I think you said it already, but
can you say again the difference between
P and Q? Is this related to the world
model versus the uh agents model? Like
the truth, the true world versus the
agents what's in the agent's head or is
it something else? Yeah, sure. No, good
question. So, um, if we were to kind of
use the phrase, is it just in the
agent's head or the world, it's all of
this would be in the agent's head. Okay.
So, yeah. Yeah. So, and then uh in the
sense that like this is the agent's
beliefs about states. This is the these
are the this is kind of the breakdown of
the overall rule of computing free
energy over states. So, states as in my
my beliefs about the world and then G
will be used for inferring what policy
should I use. So, that's as opposed to
state inference, it's policy inference,
right? Okay. So the and and and all of
it is in the in the agent's head as it
were. And then for Q and P, so Q is
always used they they always use that to
denote posteriors. So this is sort of
like what what do I think after a given
instance versus you know and versus what
did I think before, right? So there's
this kind of model inversion process
that that that happens where where we
compute f by sort of fig sorry sorry
about
this figuring out our posteriors
figuring out our relative to our priors
and that's what allows us to kind of
score the final like what is our final
belief now that that we have all of that
and we have now minimized the free
energy right so just basically employing
basian inference but in the context of a
fuller functional equation.
Yeah. Yeah. So, so you know there are a
lot of interesting ways that the these
terms get broken down and I know that
like for for a lot of folks who get
involved with the institute and their
learners uh especially those who are not
terribly uh you know comfortable with
math or or probability theory it's sort
of like these things can be very
intimidating right to just like quickly
see like you know let us tell you all at
once all these different ways you can
break down G whenever you're still
trying to learn what this little C is
over here and how what that means
relative to anything else, right? And
what's the tilda about, right? So, and
I'll also I guess I'll mention that the
tilda is uh so G what you're doing here
with G and the the whole G over pi is
you're you're inferring your beliefs
about each policy you have available
over some inference horizon which is why
we call it expected free energy. It's
that it it also is variational in the
sense of like there we're relying on
different kinds of you know approximate
methods variational methods here but the
the the expected part is emphasized
because if if if I notice I'm hungry and
I'm trying to decide what to do it's
like well if I need to if I decide one
policy I have is that I need food
there's going to be a series of steps
that I'm going to need to take. Do I
have food in my fridge? Is it at the
store? If it's at, you know, if I decide
going to the store is what I want to do,
then like what are the intermediary
steps of what I need to do from between
now and then. Um, surely I don't think
about every single thing like the entire
process of what it will be like for me
to walk down my apartment complex's
hallway, but more discreetly I know that
I will need to say stand up and then
I'll need to leave my apartment and then
I'll need to travel or take transit or
otherwise to the store and so on. So, so
it's kind of like the tilda is just
acknowledging that this is a sequence.
So, what what are the kind of
expectations I have over what will
happen if I follow a particular policy
and and how I think it will occur. So um
which is why we also don't see the tilda
up here because this is more about
momentto- moment inference which again
relates back to earlier the point about
learning right because it that's that's
an important distinction between the two
and active inference is uh state
inference is just about you know in real
time you know you think about again the
the musician playing notes in real time
and and it's very directly related to
their ability they hear the note that
they're playing versus what they think
it is. Um, so that's that's one way of
kind of just more conceptually
conceiving of uh of these things.
So, okay. And and so I guess um
especially with G, it seems to me that
the reason you would choose one
breakdown over the other, maybe with not
just G, but all of them, but um is
because you're you're trying to figure
out what's actually computable, like
based on the computing resources you
have.
Maybe it's a lot easier to compute um
that fourth line there with the expected
energy and entropy than the other
options. And in terms of uh what's
actually solvable
um that that's possible. I mean it's
never made very explicit why we have all
of these different breakdowns. The the
crucial thing is that like the way the
math plays out, it's necessarily the
case that this first line like one
version of G is information gain minus
pragmatic uh negative information gain
minus pragmatic values G. It's
necessarily going to be equivalent to
the value here um given the the
equation, right? And so it's sort of
like now another sort of tricky thing is
that the this is sort of they will be
less than or equal to these other terms.
So th this allows for almost I don't
want to get too abstract and mix things
together, but it's almost like this is
an additional like this is the the the
lower uh excuse me the upper bound of
the upper bound on like expected future
surprisal right it's because we already
know that um f from definitions of
surprise like f is just an upper bound
on surprise that that works out
mathematically and so it's kind kind of
like saying well these are the upper
bounds on surprise expected in the
future and these are kind of the upper
bound to the upper bound because of this
sneaky uh less than or equal to sign
here right um so so another thing is
that it's sort of like the another
aspect of this beyond that is u the
authors try to supply their own
definitions of the different ways of
breaking these down. Um, and so expected
free energy in just about
every as a broad generalization, but I
would I genuinely think maybe 80% to 90%
of all literature you read in active
inference, most people are just going to
focus on describing it this way,
information gain, pragmatic value
because it comes off as the most
intuitive and it's also the most
interesting in terms of viewing things
uh in like explore exploit paradigms.
It's just this is the clearest way of
kind of um
kind of expressing that and so it's it's
just intuitive like oh yes I want more
information that actually increases like
what what I thought before versus what I
know now. It's almost like I'm seeking
out. I hesitate to use the word learning
because of its its technical connotation
here, but sort of like I want to learn
more or I want to find more. You know,
it's a sort of a someone who wants to
have fun doing something new for the
sake of it. You know, I'd sort of think
about that as a more colloquial way. And
then pragmatic values just, you know, is
what I'm seeing or what I expect to see
is it going to be aligned with my
priors. So, so is what I is this
particular action, this particular
policy I'm evaluating, like going to the
store to get food, is that going to help
me achieve observations that match what
I want, which is attaining food and kind
of watching in myself eat it and then
watching my stomach no longer growl is a
kind of odd way of saying it, but it
it's closer to the the ideal of of how
it would
Yeah. Um I I think part of the the break
the breakdowns here is just sort of it's
taking into account so like with
expected ambiguity and these other terms
uh some of them additionally get
introduced in in chapter 7 as well. Um
posterior predictive entropy those kinds
of terms. is kind of like just saying
like oh it's it's sort of like this this
idea that you know there's a lot of
other dynamics of how we could view
these plane now. So expect expected
ambiguity is like um oh that that for
example is sort of what is the entropy
of what I expect to see versus what I
expect will be going on. So um you know
if if if I expect that the it will be
light
outside because I believe it's daytime
and I expect to see that it's dark
outside. So I believe that it is uh
nighttime then it's sort of like we have
this nice one to one discrete mapping.
It's light out it must be day. It's uh
dark out it must be night. Um, however,
if uh if we if we
expect more of a one to many mapping
such as uh oh, it's light outside, it
could be day or there or excuse me, it's
dark outside, it could be night, or it
could be a solar eclipse right now,
right? And I I'm just not sure which. I
didn't pay attention to the news. I
don't know like what's going on, right?
So um that's suddenly where you get more
of a one to many mapping between like
what could this particular observation
mean? Um and here it's a it's a positive
value. So we'd actually want to like
minimize that kind of that entropy of
that situation. Thus the expected
ambiguity. Um and then risk over
outcomes. So these risk terms that get
related to because there are a lot of
people who go into this field not just
because they're interested in say
neuroscience but they might be
interested in other fields. I I myself
have a a background in um I did my uh
masters at at Chicago and this very
broad social sciences program. That's
part of what part of what brought me
here uh including an interest in
economics. still looking at risk. And so
this is like your posteriors versus your
priors. Like what what do you believe
right now about what you would expect to
see versus versus pi versus like what
what do you believe after? Right? So
what what do I expect to kind of see
from what I do versus what I I I'm used
to sort of um and finding the kale
divergence between those, right? and you
want to minimize that, which is which is
a little different. So, it's just
there's so many ways to break it down
and so many different ways to attempt to
put into words why these equations work
the way they do. That's sort of the the
trick, isn't it, of not just active
inference, but sort of cognitive and
computational modeling in general. like
well if we have real data and we have
real approximate methods of mapping
things like beliefs and actions and
inference learning
processes what how do we put into
natural language what any of those
things mean.
So, it's a I think it's a fair attempt
and I I personally like many other
people kind of prefer this top one, but
it is interesting breaking the rest
down. And then it's it's kind of like
the further you go down the line here,
we get closer and closer to theoretical
physics, which is yet another kind of
partner field of academ's
um research, right? So just having
energy terms that
yeah my my background is in physics and
I think that's a large part of why this
um appealed to me is a I'm I'm working
on a robotics company. So um that's how
I came into this and found it and and
why I think it attracted me was the
analogy to physics. And
um I'm hoping to figure out some ways to
reduce the amount of data that it
requires to uh for an agent to learn a
task or to decide to do a a sequence of
motions or something.
Yeah. No, absolutely. I mean, it's uh I
don't know if you skipped ahead to
um chapter 10 in this textbook at any
point, but I think they spend some time
on on robotics and and you know the the
the more theoretical aspects of like
cybernetic processes and sort of
feedback loop operations, but then like
suddenly with active inference and this
very broad interdisciplinary aspect,
it's sort of
like because it can go so many ways it
because it comes out of neuroscience. I
mean one way one kind of funny takeaway
and maybe it's not funny but I I I think
it's kind of fun is uh like a lot of
this relates to the brain and inference
processes as well as looking at behavior
like the T-maze example that we get in
this textbook. So uh you know like a
similarly to actually having a real
mouse in a lab but then if computational
psychiatry plays into this a lot and
it's actually like it's a growing field
and many people are trying to
cognitively model and I'm working with a
research group here as well uh but we're
working on a on creating an active in
inference model of PTSD actually and uh
sort of what are the behavioral
dynamics there and and sort of the
belief dynamics. And can you
find a a generalizable but still
approximate um sort of model of these
these dynamics in relation to
neurobiology and then in future like
being able to kind of fit that model to
real empirical data that could be
collected from you know willing
participants uh who have PTSD. Um, and
and all this is to say, the reason why
I'm kind of going on about it, despite
the fact that you we started with
robotics, is that it kind of in an
interesting way, it's almost like like
is a bad machine learning model or
reinforcement learning model like if
it's bad, should we view that as a kind
of like like a pathology? Like can we
view suboptimal behavior as sort of
something like pathological behavior? So
I I just think that's a that's a
fascinating kind of take and I' I've
talked to a few people who are more
focused on sort of sort of optimizing
models rather than you know they're not
worried about attending to human beings
and modeling that they're wanting to
create very efficient you know kind of
engineering based you know tools and and
and and so on right and we've always had
interesting conversations about that
because because in active inference it's
like there's a term that's used
sometimes.
Um the term is a hyper precise prior.
And so that that would kind of be like a
scenario
where
to bring it back a little bit. It it
could be for example a situation
where skip it because you see figures.
So like imagine an agent, you know,
imagine our musician example. Again, we
don't have even have to worry about
policies just yet. Um, imagine this
agent like had a very precise
hyperparameter like on their A, like a
very strong prior for their A matrix and
for some reason they're just learning it
at either an incredibly slow rate or not
at all. Um, and say the A matrix was
really biased. So like with the with the
this example like say the agent was
heavily biased to assuming that like if
their like their these beliefs are
necessarily like onetoone with with
these to where even this kind of light
gray space didn't appear so to speak.
It's like they wouldn't track the
prediction error because they believe in
the basian sense so strongly that this
is in fact how things work, you know,
perceptually given that the HMM is just
like a perceptual model. Then it's kind
of like saying like oh that's you know
it it in in robotics that I mean that
would be awful. That means it's not able
to like read the data streams in a way
that allows it to make any kind of like
flexible adjustable inferences. instead
it's it's going to just assume whatever
it sees regardless of what it is just
reconfirms like its beliefs about you
know what's going on and if this were a
POMPP then also what it should do in
response to the data stream it's
receiving but uh simultaneously the
pathology bit is sort of like oh that
would for a musician that would mean
that they believe they're really good at
music all the time right because they're
they're sorely convinced that their
beliefs about what should be heard or
what should be played or what's going on
uh necessarily match the incoming data
stream. And so the incoming data stream
will just kind of like it won't the
variations in it won't really matter.
It's like there will still be won't even
hear that they made a mistake
essentially. They'll they'll believe
that it's right.
Exactly. And so, not to, you know, not
to sound, you know, insensitive or or or
phrase this wrongly, but it's, I mean,
if you start thinking about things like
schizophrenia or psychosis, where
something in reality is not going on at
all, but the person believes it is, it's
like in a certain way, it's they're
they're perceiving reality in a way
that's heavily biased by these kind of
priors that they're coming to the
situation with, right? So you're sort of
stuck in that uh if so long as the your
your inference process is kind of you
know kind of path pathological in that
way. So
um so yeah it's I mean with robotics I'm
not that's not my my key field as it
were. So I can't say too much other than
anytime I've skimmed it, there's always
something being something interested
being said and that you know with a lot
of these models and various areas um
they're highly performative including in
when comparing them let's say to
reinforcement learning because it's
another way of looking at active
inference especially especially POMDPS
or any any model that is actually
augmented with the capacity for action.
We're effectively just looking at okay
here's an agent who receives
observations and infers an action it
should take. Um if we just look at it as
a markov decision making process like
remove the partially observable part
then it would just kind of be like they
are it's as if they already know what
the state is. They observe a state. It's
sort of more onetoone. we don't have
this
extra observation versus states part,
right? But uh but but nonetheless, I
mean, this is still the canonical bit
because I mean this is as far as kind of
the neuroscience bits go. I mean, we're
always in a partially observable
environment, right? So we we don't
always know what an observation means
and we haven't even said anything about
like you know the possibility that the
sensory receptor itself is bad whether
it be you know a person who's
nearsighted and so anything far away is
just very hard to see or it be um you
know a robot that has a a receptor that
is just like not functioning correctly
or um an EEG headset that like you know
someone left the ground uh you know they
didn't set that up right and so it it it
sees really high amplitudes not because
of the person's neural activity it's
because it's getting like supercharged
um so in a inaccurate way so that that's
sort of the part partially observable
bit um they do I mean anytime I look
at model comparisons it's just you know
people do very regularly benchmark
Um yeah, they they regularly benchmark
these models against reinforcement
learning models. um
usually again and again, you know,
furnishing an inherent balance of
exploration and exploitation like so so
a lot of people point that out that they
just find a lot more sort of credibility
in the notion of like oh these agents
because of gee uh they're sort of
naturally internally you know
architecturally incentivized to seek out
more information. And nonetheless, like
once they're affirmed that they have
enough
information, they are over time more
than likely going to become like, oh no,
I've seen that before. So that they kind
of know not to go necessarily in that
direction. However, it's over a policy
horizon. So maybe that policy horizon is
five steps in the future or in
continuous state space. It could be, you
know, a minute into the future. uh and
what they expect to kind of see over
along the way. Um you know, so so even
if they think they've explored a space
well, they might not necessarily know
the full sequence of transitions that'll
happen over time. So that it's it's very
likely that they'll be able to depending
on your setup continuously find ways of
like getting information gain out of a
situation, computing that like
incorporating that into their decision-
making. But once they become much more
reaffirmed that they've explored enough
Then they start to, you know, I'm I'm
speaking from from experience.
Sorry. Oh, in Monterey Bay.
I'm not sure he's talking to us. No. Uh
here you go. Um so,
uh yeah, I that kind of interrupted my
sorry train of thought, but it's just to
get to the point. It's like very often
than not I I think that T-maze example
and spending just like an extra not a
long time but just like a minute or two.
Um because I know with robotics you're
usually looking at continuous streams,
right? I mean maybe there's a I mean go
sorry. Go ahead. Yeah, I was I was just
going to say yes. Um, what I would love
to be able to do is take a six degree of
freedom robot arm and output the six
joint variables
uh that are continuous, you know, and u
between some limits and um that would
all be given some sensory input and then
beliefs about what that sensory input
indicates about current state.
Yeah. No, it's incredibly relevant to a
lot of the work that is done here. And
it's sort of, you know, one way that
they break down if you if you've looked
at the book and and become more familiar
with the notion of like an observation
modality, which is, you know, a very
common sensical thing. If you get rid of
the jargon, it's just sort of like, you
know, I can see things versus feel
things versus taste things. like there
there are different ways that I can
receive information and and so they tend
to break those up into three different
categories. And so there's um
exterceptive which would be like
information I receive from the outside
which includes all the things they said
earlier that the sort of common five
senses of like I can see and touch and
feel things. Interosceptive would be
like internal bodily signals um that are
coming like sort of from within that I'm
not necessarily feeling them in the in
the typical sense of like my skin is in
you know sort of dermal aspects. Um and
then there's proprioceptive and that
that's if you come across that term or
sorry by the way I don't mean to sound
condescending if you already are
familiar with it. No no this is great.
Thank you. Cool. Definitely. Yeah. So,
so proprioceptive I'm just trying to
find a quick and we might have to wrap
up then is
uh I know it's in
here. Um somewhere there's there's they
have a nice sort of visual description
of like the idea of like this
proprioceptive afrin. So this is you
know this is still related to more like
the brain but
proprioception you know it has much more
to do with like movement and kind of
reactive systems. So so there could be
like a reflex arc sort of logic for
example
um that that might be of interest to you
if you want a model that's kind of a
little bit more complex or sort of sort
of savvy with with putting together the
architecture in regards to active
inference. There's no necessity of it
though and I think you'll you'll you
might especially find chapter eight
interesting which is going to explicitly
go over continuous models. It of course
is different because of the continuous
spa like time and continuous state space
sort of setup. Um but then in that case
we're looking at more like kind of these
attracting points or or here this is uh
this is rather complex but this is a
Lawrence you know chaotic system and
sort of like different kinds of dynamics
and viewing them in different ways and
viewing how you know like I mentioned
with the discrete state space setting
there's C which is sort of defining your
goals or your expected observations you
want um the the sort of equivalent of
that in continuous state space models.
You could view that as uh is sort of
like an attracting point or or a
distribution of attracting points or an
attracting distribution uh over a
continuous space than just modeling it
like that. Um you'll also it it relies a
lot more on sort of tailaylor series
approximations. There's this notion he
calls refers to it as the uh uh
generalized coordinates of motion. So
it's sort of like there these more sort
of working more with more directly and
explicitly with derivatives um over
time. So um yeah it's yeah I realized
that that actually kind of shot by the
time um but uh thanks for this uh
opportunity to get into uh to sort of
the deeper theoretics and and and really
honing in on some of these equations. Uh
yeah, you know, some Yeah, it's
sometimes folks with the here I'll I'll
uh pause. Um also, thanks for bearing
with the uh this is my first time ever
when I'm doing this purely solo,
so yeah. Um, so I'll go ahead and stop
recording and thank you everyone and see
you at the next See you at the next